Hello, I'm Dr. Sonia
Rivera-Martinez, Associate
Professor, Department
of Family Medicine,
and today I will be discussing
clinical dyslipidemia.
Our session objectives
are as follows.
We will describe the
main features for the
different types of
lipopropine disorders,
and then explain their
role in disease. 1.
Identify the main features for
primary causes of dyslipidemia.
2. Examine the
main features for
secondary causes
of dyslipidemia.
Then we will correlate
the presenting
signs and symptoms
with the different
types of dyslipidemia
disorders.
And lastly, we will
explain the rationale
for the different
preventative strategies for
dyslipidemia disorders
and formulate a
treatment plan based on
the latest guidelines.
We will now proceed
with the definition
and classification
of dyslipidemia.
Disorders of lipoprotein
metabolism can be primary,
caused by genetic conditions,
or secondary to other
medical conditions or
environmental exposure and involve
either of substantial increase
or decrease in specific
circulating lipids or
lipoproteins. Lipoprotein
disorders can have a number
of clinical consequences.
Lipoproteins are
complexes of lipids and
proteins. They are
essential for transport of
cholesterol, triglycerides,
and fat-soluble vitamins
in the blood. They
also play essential
roles in the absorption
of dietary cholesterol,
long-chain fatty acids,
and fat-soluble vitamins.
There are several
classes of lipoproteins
which are classified primarily
by their lipid
content per particle.
Chylomicrons, they are
considered to be the
least dense lipoprotein,
meaning that they are
the most lipid rich.
On the other hand, high
-density lipoprotein has
the least lipid content.
This image demonstrates the
relationship of lipoproteins
by density and size, which
are inversely related.
You can see that the
HDL is the smallest
lipoprotein, but yet
it's high in density,
contrary to the
chylomicron, which is the
largest in size but
has the least density.
Lipoproteins are involved
in the transport of lipids.
Chylomicrons, they
transport dietary lipids
from the intestine
to the periphery and
liver which are used
in energy and storage.
LDL and LDL are involved
in the transport
of hepatic lipids to
the periphery. In other
words, from the liver
to the periphery.
The HDL is involved
in transport of
excess VLDL, IDL, and
LDL from the periphery
back to the liver
for processing.
In the exogenous
pathway, chylomicrons
transport dietary fat
from the intestine to
tissues that require
fatty acids for energy
and storage and
cholesterol to the liver.
In the endogenous pathway,
hepatic lipids are
transported from
the liver to the
periphery to provide
a source of energy
during fasting.
HDL pathway transports
excess cholesterol from the
periphery back to the
liver for excretion in the
bile. Only hepatocytes
and enterocytes can
effectively excrete cholesterol
from the body. In the
liver, cholesterol is
secreted into the bile either
directly or after
conversion to bile acids and
pterocytes excrete cholesterol
into the gut lumen.
We will now move
on to dyslipidemia
and its role in disease.
The clinical significance
for dyslipidemia
is that they can contribute to
the development of
antherosclerosis.
Antherosclerosis is a
known factor in coronary
artery disease, peripheral
vascular disease,
and cerebrovascular
accidents. All of these
can cause significant
problems for the patients
who have them, including
leading to death.
Severe hyper
triglyceridemia may lead to
acute pancreatitis.
The clinical element in
this is non-alcoholic
fatty liver disease.
Anthrosclerosis is a
very common disease that
affects the arteries
and is caused by buildup
of cholesterol plaques.
These plaques are
formed by macrophages
and LDL being accumulated
and forming a
complex antheromas.
Complications of
these formations
is ischemia, thrombosformation,
emboli, and aneurysms
in the areas affected.
Symptoms for the
patients include angina,
claudication,
and often asymptomatic.
Atheromas tend to form
in areas of the arteries
that are exposed to
increased shear stress,
such as bifurcations and
bending points leading
to the exposure of the
subendothelial tissue.
Platelet aggregates or
microthrombi form due to
platelet adherence to the
exposed subendothelial tissue.
These events initiate a
cascade that eventually
leads to the formation
of antheromas.
Risk factors for developing
antherosclerosis include
age, which progressive
with each decade of life.
Male gender is more affected
than the female gender.
Family history of a patient
that includes hypertension,
diabetes,
or familial
hypercholesterolemia
increases this patient's risk.
Cigarette smoking of the
affected patient would also
increase the risk. This
is a modifiable risk
factor. Patients who stopped
smoking would improve and
decrease the risk of
developing antherosclerosis.
The presence in the
patient of hypertension,
whether it is
systolic or diastolic,
Hyperlipidemia, which is
when primarily the LDL
is elevated and also the
low HDL, which the low
HDL is an independent
risk factor on its own.
Presence of diabetes
or metabolic syndrome.
Metabolic syndrome
is a group of risk
factors and it's
defined by three or more
of the following
five abnormalities.
The presence of fasting
blood glucose of greater
than or equal to 100
milligrams per deciliter, a
blood pressure of at least
130 over 85 milligrams,
triglycerides that are
greater or equal to 150
milligrams per deciliter,
HDL of a level of less than
40 milligrams per deciliter
in men or less than 50
milligrams per deciliter
in women, and a waist
circumference of 40 inches
in men or 35 inches in women.
We will now move on to discuss
the ideology of dyslipidemia.
Primary causes of
dyspidemia generally are
single or multiple gene
mutations which result
in either overproduction
or defective clearance
of triglycerides and
LDL cholesterol, or
underproduction or
excessive clearance of HDL.
Familial hypercholesterolemia
is a primary cause
of dyslipidemia. It is
resulted due to a gene defect
in the LDL receptor,
which causes diminished
clearance of LDL. The
inheritance is codominant,
customarily, or complex with
multiple gene involvement.
The prevalence for
heterozygotes is 1 in
200 and homozygotes
in 1 in every 250,000
to 1 in every 1 million.
In heterozygotes,
you generally see total
cholesterol between 250 and
500 milligrams per
deciliter. There is premature
coronary artery disease
between the ages of 30 to
50, and in 5%, there is
a myocardial infarction
before 60 years old. In
homozygotes, the triglycerides
are greater than, excuse
me, the total cholesterol
is greater than 500
milligrams per deciliter.
And there is also
premature coronary artery
disease, which occurs
before the age of 18.
Familial combined
hyperlipidemia is another
primary cause of
dysplipidemia. The genetic
defect that is involved
in this case is unknown.
It is possible that there are
multiple defects involved.
The inheritance is autosomal.
The prevalence is between
1 in 150 to 1 in 100.
There is premature coronary
artery disease, resulting
in 15% of MIs in people
less than 50 years old.
ApoB is disproportionately
elevated.
Total cholesterol
customarily is
between 250 and 500,
and triglycerides
are customarily
between 250 and 750.
Continuing with primary
causes of dyslipidemia,
we have familial
hypertriglyceridemia.
Its genetic defect is
unknown. It is likely
that it is caused by
multiple genetic defects
and mechanisms. It has
an autosomal dominant
inheritance and a
prevalence of 1 out of 500.
It customarily has no
symptoms or findings.
There is absence of
secondary causes to make
this diagnosis, and
the triglycerides are
between 200 and 500
milligrams per deciliter.
Another primary cause
of distalipinemia is
familial defective
ApoB100. The genetic defect
involved here is LDL
receptor binding region
defect which causes
diminished clearance of LDL.
Its inheritance is autosomal
dominant. It is
prevalent in 1 in 700.
It also has premature
coronary artery disease.
There are symptomas and arches
carnea present
on physical exam.
The total cholesterol
is between 250
and 500 milligrams
per deciliter.
Familial HDL deficiency
is another primary cause
of dyslipidemia. Its genetic
defect is ABCA1 gene,
ATP binding cassette
transporter A1.
The inheritance is autosomal
dominant, the prevalence
is rare, and coronary
artery disease is also seen.
Moving on now to secondary
causes of dyslipidemia.
Secondary causes
contribute to many
cases of dyslipidemias
in adults.
The most important
secondary cause in
developed countries
is a sedentary
lifestyle. This is
totally modifiable.
It includes an excessive
dietary intake of
saturated fat,
cholesterol, and trans fat.
modifying diet can
modify this important
secondary cause
of dyslipidemia.
Other common secondary causes
of dyslipidemia include
endocrine disorders such
as diabetes mellitus,
insulin resistance, Cushing's
disease and hypothyroidism.
There are hepatic disorders
such as primary biliary
cirrhosis and other
cholestatic liver diseases.
Renal disorders,
which include chronic
kidney disease and
nephrotic syndrome.
Medications, there are
many culprits here,
including thiazides,
beta blockers, retinoids,
highly active
antiretroviral agents,
estrogen and progestins, and
corticosteroids. Other
causes include diet,
obesity,
and alcohol overuse.
Diabetes mellitus is a
significant secondary cause
of dyslipidemia. It has an
antherogenic combination
of elevated triglycerides
and LDL and low HDL.
This is exacerbated
by the precedence of
obesity, sedentary
life or physical
inactivity, and
increased caloric intake.
Another secondary
cause of dyslipidemia
is excessive hepatic
production of VLDL.
This is characterized
by elevated fasting
triglycerides, low HDL,
and variable levels of LDL.
Common causes include high
carbohydrate diet, obesity
and insulin resistance, in
which more free fatty acids
are delivered from the
adipose tissue to the liver,
and there is increased
insulin levels which
promote increased
fatty acid synthesis.
Also, as seen, neprotic
syndrome and Cushing syndrome.
Alcohol overuse is another
secondary cause
of dyslipinemia.
It causes excessive production
of VLDL in the liver.
It inhibits hepatic
oxidation of free fatty
acids and promotes
hepatic triglyceride
synthesis and that of
LDL VLDL secretion.
It rises the plasma
levels of HDL.
Consider this if you
see a combination
of elevated
triglycerides and HDL.
Continuing with secondary
causes of dyslipidemia,
we have here impaired
lipolysis of triglyceride
rich lipoproteins.
This occurs due to
decreased LPL or
lipoprotein lipase activity.
It is characterized by
elevated fasting triglycerides,
low HDL, usually without
elevations of LDL or APLB.
Common causes of this is
obesity and insulin resistance.
The impaired hepatic uptake
of lipoproteins containing
APLB is another secondary
cause of dyslipidemia.
Here you see
reduced LDL receptor
activity, characterized
by elevated LDL.
Common causes of this
is hypothyroidism,
in which there is
increased IDL and mild
elevation of
triglycerides, also seen in
chronic kidney disease
in which there is mild
hypertriglyceridemia
which is less
than 300 milligrams
per deciliter.
Reduced HDL levels is
considered another secondary
cause of dyslipidemia. This
is caused by a combination
of genetic prediposition
and secondary factors.
This is an independent
predictor for
increased cardiovascular
risk all by itself.
HDL metabolism is
influenced by triglyceride
-rich lipoproteins,
insulin resistance,
and inflammation. Secondary
causes of low levels
of HDL cholesterol
include cigarette smoking,
anabolic steroids,
HIV infection, and
neurotic syndrome.
Certain liver disorders
and drugs are also
within the secondary
causes of dyslipidemia.
For the liver
disorders, we have
hepatitis, which can be
caused by infections,
drugs, or alcohol,
which are associated
with increased
VLDL synthesis and
mild to moderate
hypertriglycyremia.
Cholestasis is associated
with hypercholesterolemia,
which can be severe.
Drugs that are
included in this group
are beta blockers, which
reduce HDL and you see
also elevated VLDL.
With thiazides you will see
an elevated LDL and with
estrogens you will see
elevated HDL, elevated VLDL,
and triglycerides. These
are all common medications,
so make sure that you are
aware of these effects.
Our next topic is signs and
symptoms related
to dyslipidemia.
Dyslipidemia in
itself is usually
asymptomatic. No symptoms
are present. However,
it leads to symptomatic
vascular disease,
which includes coronary
artery disease, stroke,
peripheral arterial disease.
Note that an extremely
high triglyceride levels
can give a lactase
appearance to blood plasma.
Symptoms when this
is present are
paresthesias, dyspnea,
and confusion.
You can see here a
tube that of someone
that has very high
levels of triglycerides.
Take note that high
levels of triglycerides,
meaning greater than
1,000 milligrams
per deciliter can cause
acute pancreatitis.
Take note again,
severe elevations of
triglycerides can present
with eruptive symptoms
over the trunk,
back, elbow, buttocks,
knees, hands, and feet.
Severe hypertriglycerinia
greater than 2,000 milligrams
per deciliter can present
with lipemia retinalis.
High levels of LDL can
present with arcus cornea
and tendinosis as depicted
here in this picture.
Physical exam findings for
hypercholesterolemia include
tendinosis xanthomas.
These begins with tendon
thickening at the lateral
border. Occur mainly in the
extensor tendons of the hands,
feet, elbows, and knees.
You can can also see
tuberous xanthomas. These are
firm, painless yellow or red
nodules which are usually
found over extensor aspects
of the limbs and buttocks.
Other physical exam findings
for hypercholesterolemia
includes Arcus cornea
which results from
cholesterol infiltration
of the corneal rim.
Xanthelesmas are yellow
cholesterol plaques that occur
most commonly near the inner
canthus, usually of the
upper eyelid. Both of these
are very common findings.
Physical exam findings
for hypertriglycyremia
includes eruptive
than xanthomas.
These are painless
yellow papules
that present as
groups of lesions
on the torso,
elbows, chest, and buttocks.
Our next topic in
this presentation
includes diagnosis
of dyslipidemia.
Clinical manifestations
of dyslipidemia may
present as one or
more of the following.
Elevated total
plasma cholesterol,
elevated low
-density lipoprotein,
elevated triglycerides, and
decreased high
-density lipoprotein.
The diagnosis for
dyslipidemia is
done by measuring serum lipids.
The serum lipid
profile includes
total cholesterol,
triglycerides,
HDL cholesterol,
and calculated LDL cholesterol
and VLDL cholesterol.
The formula is
total cholesterol
equals VLDL plus LDL plus HDL.
Note that in a
serum lipid profile,
total cholesterol,
triglycerides, and
HDL cholesterol are
measured directly.
Total cholesterol
values can vary by 10%
and triglycerides by
up to 25% day to day,
even in the absence
of a disorder. So it's
normal that you would
see this variation.
Patients should have
all lipids measured
while fasting,
usually for 12 hours,
for maximum accuracy
and consistency.
Again, they should
have the levels done
while fasting for
at least 12 hours.
Testing should be postponed
until after resolution of
acute illness. This is
because triglycerides and
lipoprotein levels increase
and cholesterol levels decrease
when there is the presence
of an inflammatory state.
The LDL cholesterol
is customarily
calculated in a
serum lipid profile.
This calculation the LDL
equals the total cholesterol
minus the HDL plus the
triglycerides divided by five.
This calculation is valid
only when triglycerides are
less than 400 milligrams
per deciliters and patients
are fasting because eating
increases triglycerides.
You can request a
direct LDL measurement
when the triglycerides
are greater
than 400 milligrams
per deciliter.
Direct LDL measurements
are not routinely necessary
because the LDL calculated
one is approximately
the same when the triglycerides
are less than 400.
So they're close to
being very accurate.
Screening for dyslipidemia.
Universal screening
use a fasting lipid profile
should be done in once
for all children between
the age of 9 and 11 or at
2 if children have a
family history of severe
hyperlipidemia or premature
coronary artery disease.
Adults are screened at age 20
and every five
years thereafter.
Assessment for cardiovascular
risk factors should accompany
the lipid measurements.
A definite age to discontinue
screening has not
been determined.
It should be noted that
screening in certain circumstance
can be done more frequently
than is noted here.
Screening for secondary
causes of dyslipidemia
should be considered
with newly diagnosed
dyslipidemia and or
when a component of the
lipid profile has changed
for the worth without
an explanation. Consider
fasting glucose,
liver enzymes,
creatinine, thyroid stimulating
hormone, and urinary protein.
Once secondary causes ruled
out, attempt to determine
if there are primary
causes of dyslipidemia.
For the diagnosis
of primary cause of
a dyslipidemia in
chylomicronemia, you
would do this with
the fasting plasma.
And if there is the presence
of a triglyceride level
of greater than a thousand
milligrams per deciliter, you
can consider familial
chylomicronemia syndrome in
which the cholesterol to
triglyceride ratio is greater
than 10 and these individuals
would be at risk for acute
pancreatitis as noted
previously. For familial
hypercholesterolemia, LDL levels
are elevated in the absence
of hypertriglycidemia. This
is a clinical diagnosis.
Combined hyperlipidemia is
another primary cause of
dyslipidemia. It It is
diagnosed by obtaining an
elevation of triglycerides,
VLDL and LDL in serum lipids.
You would determine the
VLDL to triglyceride ratio
in plasma or direct
LDL to determine if the
hyperlipidemia is due to
accumulation of lipoprotein
revenants, that is in familial
dysbeta-lipoproteinemia,
or an increase in both
LDL and VLDL is present.
The measurement of APOB
levels can help identify
patients with familial
combined hyperlipidemia.
We will now move on to
the American College of
Cardiology and American
Heart Association Task
Force Clinical Practice
Guidelines from 2026.
According to the AHCC
and AHA guidelines of
2026, the main indication
for treatment of
dyslipidemia is the
prevention of ASCVD or
antherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease, including
acute coronary syndrome,
stroke, transient
ischemic attack, and
peripheral vascular disease.
The current guidelines
recommend treating
dyslipidemia earlier to
reduce the lifelong risk of
prolonged exposure to
anthrogenic lipoprotein.
These treatment guidelines
include lifestyle
optimization that should
start in youth, including
childhood. Consider
pharmacotherapy in youth with
familial hypercholesterolemia
and in young adults
with an LDC of greater
than 160 milligrams per
deciliter or family
history of premature ASCVD.
They also recommend to
use the AHA Prevent Risk
Calculator to determine the
10-year risk of ASCVD. The
primary prevention of
ASCVD with LDL medication
therapy in adults should
begin with a prevent
ASCVD risk estimate of
3-2 less than 5% and
should be considered for
those having a 5%-2 less
than 10% risk. Testing
for apolopoprotein B can
improve risk assessment,
particularly in
individuals with elevated
triglycerides or diabetes.
Lipoprotein A should be
assessed at least once
to determine individuals
at risk for ASCVD.
A coronary artery calcium
scoring can be beneficial
in men at least 40 years
old and women at 45 year
old, which can improve the
assessment and guide LDL-C
and non-HDLC goals. ldl
lowering therapy is recommended
as primary prevention
in adults between 40 and
75 years old with diabetes
chronic kidney disease
stage 3 or 4 or hiv in
secondary prevention a goal of
LDL-C less than 55 milligrams
per deciliter and non
-HDL-C less than 85
milligrams per deciliter is
recommended for those at very
high risk of ASCVD events.
In secondary prevention,
a goal of LDL-C of less
than 55 milligrams per
deciliter and non
-HDL-C of less than 85
milligrams per deciliter
is recommended for those
individuals at very high
risk of ASCVD events.
Patients with persistently
elevated triglycerides
statin therapy still
remains the foundation
pharmacotherapy along with
lifestyle intervention to reduce
ASCVD risk. In individuals
with triglyceride levels
of greater than 1,000
milligrams per deciliter,
treatment with triglyceride
lowering therapies
helps prevent
The American Heart
Association and the American
College of Cardiology
recommends treatment with a
statin for four specific
group of patients in the
presence of clinical
anthrosclerotic cardiovascular
disease. When the LDL LDL
cholesterol is greater
than or equal to 190
milligrams per deciliter.
In patients ages 40 to
75 with diabetes and
LDL cholesterol between
70 to 189 milligrams
per deciliter. Here,
the treatment goal
is less than 70
milligrams per deciliter.
Age 40 to 75 with an LDL
cholesterol between 70 and 189
milligrams per deciliter
and an estimated 10-year
antherosclerotic cardiovascular
disease of 7.5% or more.
The risk of antherosclerotic
cardiovascular
disease is estimating
using a risk
calculator that
takes into account.
and this risk calculator is
from the American College
of Cardiology and the
American Heart Association.
It includes the sex
of the patient, age,
race, total cholesterol
and HDL cholesterol,
the systolic and
diastolic blood pressure,
use of antihypertensives
or statins,
presence or absence
of diabetes,
and smoker status.
All of these are
combined to come
up with the risk calculation.
In addition to the
risk calculation by the
calculator from the American
College of Cardiology
and the American Heart
Association, other
factors can be considered
to determine a need
for a statin. LDL
cholesterol that is greater
to or equal to 160
milligrams per deciliter.
Familial history of
premature coronary artery
disease, which would
be the onset of less
than 55 years old in a
male who is first-degree
relative or the onset
of less than 65 year
old in a female who is
first-degree relative.
A
high-sensitivity C-reactive
protein of greater to
or equal to two milligrams
per deciliter, a coronary
artery calcium score of
greater than or equal to
300 Agotson units or
greater than 75 percentile,
ankle brachial blood
pressure index of less than 0
.9, and also the increased
lifetime risk based on the
ACCAHA risk calculator.
We will now go on to discuss
dyslipidemia
treatment. treatment.
The goals for treatment
of lipoprotein disorders
include prevention of
cardiovascular disease
and related cardiovascular
events, prevention
of acute pancreatitis
in patients with severe
hypertriglycerinia, note that
these are only two major goals.
In considering a treatment
plan for lipoprotein disorders,
you perform a risk
assessment and take in
consideration life changes,
which is first line of
treatment, exercise and
dietary modifications.
Next, if there are
elevated LDL. You
can use statins,
bioacids, sequestrin,
ezetimide, and
niacin to help treat.
And in elevated triglycerides,
you can use niacin,
fibrates, or meta-3 fatty
acids for treatment.
In the management of
hypercholesterolemia,
consider lifestyle changes.
So if obese, assist
patient with reduction of
weight to the ideal level
based on their height. 8.
Include aerobic exercise. Don't
forget that walking
is also exercise.
9.
Reduce intake of saturated fat,
trans fat,
and cholesterol. All
of these measures can
assist with reduction
of hypercholesterolemia.
Also, in addition to
reduction of intake of
the items mentioned
before, increase the
intake of fiber and
complex carbohydrates.
In the management of
hypercholesterolemia,
statins are considered
the treatment of
choice for the reduction
of LDL cholesterol.
This medication
assists with the
reduction of cardiovascular
risk, is well
supported by
clinical trial data.
Statins are HMG
-choliductase inhibitors.
They work by inhibiting
the rate-limiting step
enzyme in cholesterol
biosynthesis. This leads
to significantly reducing
LDL and generally
also have a modest increase
in HDL cholesterol.
statins are generally
well tolerated.
They, like any
other medication,
have side effects
and the more common
ones are dyspepsia,
headache, fatigue.
Muscle or joint pain occurs
in a lot of patients.
There are elevation of liver
enzyme levels, which need
to be closely monitored at
least every three months.
Lifestyle modifications
is considered
first-line management
for hypertriglyceridemia.
Again, lifestyle modification.
If obese, reduce weight
to ideal level and also
do aerobic exercise. This
is for your patients.
The dietary modifications
include reduce intake
of alcohol, preferably
eliminate the intake,
and also reduce the intake
of simple carbohydrates.
On the other hand, And
increase the intake
of omega-3 fatty acids,
such as marine fish.
In diabetics, ensure tight
control of glucose levels.
Remind patients of this one.
Take note of this.
In the management of
hypertriglyceridemia, only if
lifestyle management has failed,
again, only if lifestyle
management has failed,
then you initiate
medications for patients with
persistent triglyceride
levels greater than 500
milligrams per deciliter. You
do not treat triglycerides
less than 500 milligrams
per deciliter. You treat
only if it is above 500
milligrams per deciliter.
Use fibric acid
derivatives for treatment.
The side effects can be
myopathy, gallstones. There can
be creatinine elevations.
also note that these
medications may rise the LDL
level omega-3 fatty acids have
a side effect generally of
dyspepsia they may prolong
bleeding time so take note
of that but generally these
medications are well
tolerated nicotinic acid. The
side effect also is dyspepsia
and it also may elevate
uric acid and liver transaminase
which are AST and ALT.
Key points to remember.
Elevated lipid levels
are a risk factor for
antherosclerosis as
discussed previously.
Causes of dyslipidemia
include sedentary
lifestyle with
excessive dietary
intake and or
genetic abnormality.
Of course the
sedentary lifestyle and
excessive dietary
intake. Both of these
are modifiable. Consider
those initially.
Diagnose dyslipidemia using
fasting serum lipid profile.
Screening tests should be
done at age 9 to 11, age
2 if there is strong
family history of severe
hyperlipidemia, or premature
coronary artery disease.
And lastly, screen adults
every five years after age 20.
Please note the core
references for this
lecture which are Harrison's
internal medicine,
principles of
internal medicine, and
dyslipidemia, endocrine,
and metabolic disorders
of Merck-Manuel's
professional our edition.
Thank you all.
Please use the link for
lecture feedback. Thank you.